{"tossups": [{"question": "This man allegedly ordered each of his soldiers to kill 24 civilians, resulting in a bloody massacre outside Urgench. Territories conquered by this man were governed by the Yassa code and included the Khwarazmian Empire. This man launched a campaign against the Western Xia and Jin dynasties, though his conquest of China was completed by his grandson. For ten points, name this founder of the Mongolian Empire and grandfather of Kublai Khan.", "answer": "<b> Genghis</b> Khan (accept<b> Temujin</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Frank DiPascali worked for 33 years under this man, who Genevievette Walker-Lightfoot attempted to investigate. Jeffry Picower was the largest beneficiary from this man\u2019s core business, which led Picower to hand over $7.2 billion gained from it. This man was arrested after he told his son Mark that his business was \u201cone big lie,\u201d and he was sentenced to 150 years in prison in 2009. The New York Mets were among the victims of, for ten points, what fraudster who operated the largest Ponzi scheme in U.S. history?", "answer": "Bernard Lawrence \u201cBernie\u201d<b> Madoff</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Because he could not swim, this man was forced to awkwardly paddle around in water wings when Mao Zedong insisted on meeting in a swimming pool. This leader made a controversial declaration at the Polish Embassy in Moscow, and he protested Lorenzo Sumulong\u2019s address to the UN by banging his shoe on a desk. This man, who denounced the cult of personality of his predecessor in the 1956 \u201cSecret Speech,\u201d presided over the Cuban Missile Crisis. For ten points, name this Soviet premier who succeeded Joseph Stalin in 1953.", "answer": "Nikita<b> Khrushchev</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The protagonist of this work finds solace in the fact that \u201chis wife and little ones are still beyond the invader\u2019s farthest advance.\u201d At the end of this work, a figure swings \u201cgently from side to side beneath the timbers\u201d of the central location in northern Alabama. The protagonist struggles to free himself of a noose as he falls into the water in, for ten points, what short story about Confederate supporter Peyton Farquhar, written by Ambrose Bierce?", "answer": "An<b> Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "Cyclists traversing this island usually take about two weeks to go the over 800 miles from Land\u2019s End to John o\u2019 Groats, taking motorways like the M5, which opened in 1962. In a 1967 paper that predated his coining of the term \u201cfractal,\u201d Benoit Mandelbrot discussed the length of this island\u2019s coast. The Antonine Wall and Hadrian\u2019s Wall were built on, for ten points, what largest European island that is home to the countries of Scotland, Wales, and England?", "answer": "Great<b> Britain</b> (do not accept England, UK, etc.)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1511, a force from this country led by Alfonso de Albuquerque captured the city of Malacca. Prior to 1975, this country controlled East Timor, and prior to 1961, it controlled the city of Goa. An explorer from this country was the first European to reach the Cape of Good Hope in South Africa. Explorers Vasco da Gama and Bartolomeu Dias were from, for ten points, what country where Prince Henry the Navigator sponsored explorations as a rival to its neighbor, Spain?", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This university\u2019s Ryerson Physical Laboratory was the site where Robert Millikan conducted his oil drop experiment in 1909. Sergio de Castro became a Minister of Finance after studying at this school as part of the Chile Project. A series of 1962 sit-ins at this university were organized by then-student Bernie Sanders. For ten points, name this university where Milton Friedman was a member of a prominent school of economics in Illinois.", "answer": "University of<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man ordered grapeshot to be fired on his own soldiers to win the tightly contested Battle of Guilford Courthouse. Though he often feuded with his superior Henry Clinton, this man was able to embarrass Horatio Gates at Camden. After one battle, this man claimed he was sick and sent his second in command, Charles O\u2019Hara, to surrender instead. For ten points, name this British commander who was defeated by Comte de Rochambeau and George Washington at Yorktown.", "answer": "Charles<b> Cornwallis</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Hekla 3 Eruption may have caused the end of this period. The Yamna Culture existed during the early stages of this period. The Hittites and Mycenaeans fell apart during this period\u2019s namesake collapse. This period was the second in a classification scheme laid out by the antiquarian Christian Thomsen based on the artifacts used by people at the time. For ten points, name this period that succeeded the Stone Age and preceded the Iron Age.", "answer": "<b> Bronze Age</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This instrument was the original medium for<em> Le tombeau de Couperin</em>, a suite dedicated to friends who fought and died in World War I, before it was orchestrated by its composer. The brother of philosopher Ludwig Wittgenstein, Paul, played this instrument professionally; in 1929, he commissioned a D major\u201cConcerto for the Left Hand\u201d for this instrument, as he had lost his right arm in World War I. For ten points, name this musical instrument whose grand variety includes 88 keys.", "answer": "<b> piano</b>forte", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man killed his own horse to show that he would not run prior to his last stand at the Silarius River. Earlier, this man used rope vines to surprise the forces of Gaius Glaber while defending his home base of Mount Vesuvius. After this man was defeated, he and his supporters were crucified along the Appian Way. For ten points, name this gladiator who led a 73 BC revolt against the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b> Spartacus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Scholars recognize that this book was written as the second volume of a work, of which Luke is the first volume. In the early part of this book, the Holy Spirit descends upon the Christians in Jerusalem, who begin speaking in tongues. Later in this book, Saul changes his name to Paul after being blinded on the road to Damascus. For ten points, name this book detailing the history of the first-century Christian church, which immediately follows the Gospels in the New Testament.", "answer": "<b> Acts</b> of the Apostles", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man defeated Louis-Eugene Cavaignac, the general who put down the June Days uprising, in a presidential election. This man, who employed Baron Haussmann to redesign</b> <b>his capital, sponsored a failed attempt to place (+)</b> <b>Maximilian on the throne of Mexico.</b> <b>This ruler took personal command in a campaign that enjoyed a major victory at (*) </b>Solferino, but he was forced to abdicate after his capture at Sedan during a war with Prussia. For ten points, name this last Emperor of France.", "answer": "<b> Napoleon III</b> (or<b> Louis-Napoleon</b> Bonaparte; do not prompt on Napoleon alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>As a twelve-year-old, this man once personally called Bill Hewlett of Hewlett-Packard for parts to build a frequency counter. Tim Berners-Lee ran the first browser on the World Wide Web using a device created by this man\u2019s company (+) NeXT Inc. This man became a member of Disney\u2019s board of directors following the purchase of (*)</b> Pixar, of which he was CEO. This man is most famous for founding a company that sold \u201cNano\u201d and \u201cShuffle\u201d versions of its iPod. For ten points, name this late co-founder and CEO of Apple.", "answer": "Steve<b> Jobs</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>This organization was named for a chief of the Lenape tribe and accordingly granted the title of \u201cGrand Sachem\u201d upon its leaders. This organization turned off the lights in meetings</b> <b>to stifle dissidents, leading their opposition to be called the (+)</b> <b>Locofocos. A leader of</b> <b>this organization died in Ludlow Jail after he was deported from Spain; locals in Spain recognized him thanks to (*) </b> cartoons from Thomas Nast. For ten points, name this notoriously corrupt New York political machine once headed by Boss Tweed.", "answer": "<b> Tammany Hall</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This artist rose to prominence for a depiction of a crowd being led away before Philip III, though that portrayal was lost in a fire. A row of vertical pikes are held by men behind</b> <b>Ambrogio Spinola in this artist\u2019s depiction of a battle in the (+)</b> <b>Eighty Years War,</b><em><b> The</b></em> <b>Eighty Years War,</b><em><b> The</b></em> <em><b>Surrender of Breda</b></em><b>. This court painter for Philip IV depicted that king\u2019s (*)</b> <em><b>Surrender of Breda</b></em><b>. This court painter for Philip IV depicted that king\u2019s (*)</b> daughter, Margaret Theresa, being attended to by maids of honor in his most famous work. For ten points, name this painter of<em> Las Meninas</em>.", "answer": "Diego<b> Velasquez</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>William Richardson was the first person to receive a land grant in this city, in which he names a bay. A popular destination of bootleggers during Prohibition was the fishing village</b> <b>of Sausalito near this city. A dangerous (+)</b> <b>neighborhood in this city received its name</b> <b>after policemen working in it claimed you could afford a high-quality steak from working shifts in it. This home of the (*)</b> Tenderloin District is also home to a one end of a structure designed by Joseph Strauss and Charles Ellis that links it to Marin County by crossing a namesake bay. For ten points, name this home city of the Golden Gate Bridge.", "answer": "<b> San Francisco</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A governor of this city committed suicide after being unable to stop the</b><em><b> HMS Phaeton </b></em><b>from harassing ships in its harbor. Inhabitants of this city nicknamed arriving carracks\u201cblack ships\u201d while it was briefly under Portuguese rule. During a period of seclusion, only</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Dutch traders were allowed to trade with this city via its artificially built Dejima</b> <b>Island. Because cloud cover obscured Kokura, the (*)</b> Fat Man weapon was used against, for ten points, what city that was attacked with a nuclear weapon three days after Hiroshima?", "answer": "<b> Nagasaki</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man agreed to put his troops under the command of the Australian John Monash during the Battle of Hamel. During his early service, this man captured Datu Amil in the</b> <b>Moro Rebellion and fought with the (+)</b> <b>Buffalo Soldiers of the 10th Cavalry, granting</b> <b>Buffalo Soldiers of the 10th Cavalry, granting</b> <b>him his nickname. This man later led the Punitive Expedition to (*)</b> <b>him his nickname. This man later led the Punitive Expedition to (*)</b> avenge the raid on Columbus and sought to capture Pancho Villa in 1916. For ten points, name this leader of the American Expeditionary Force in World War I, a general nicknamed \u201cBlack Jack.\u201d", "answer": "John \u201cBlack Jack\u201d<b> Pershing</b>  (1) <b>Army officers stationed in this country threatened to resign in the Curragh</b> <b>incident. Charles Stewart Parnell created a party for this nation and fought for</b> <b>its independence. This country\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Home Rule movement was advocated for by</b> <b>Home Rule movement was advocated for by</b> <b>William Gladstone in the House of Commons. The repeal of the (*)</b> <b>William Gladstone in the House of Commons. The repeal of the (*)</b> Corn Laws was prompted by a food shortage in this country that killed nearly a million people. For ten points, name this island that was controversially ruled by its neighbor, Great Britain, in the 19th century. ANSWER:<b> Ireland</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}